Guide to the New York City League for Sexual Freedom and The Feminists files, circa 1964-1970.
New York City League for Sexual Freedom and The Feminists files
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
New York City League for Sexual Freedom and The Feminists files, circa 1964-1970.
7844
Goring, William.
0.1
Correspondence, newspapers, printed materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files about the NYC League for Sexual Freedom, all from 1964, including a proposal for its structure dated 20 April 1964, and a pink mimeographed rough draft of this proposal with handwritten notes. Seven letters to and from Goring about the League, 1 from Jefferson Poland. Danny Sloan wrote to William Goring about Sloan's recent broadcast with Barry Gray on December 14th. On the letterhead, Allen Ginsberg and others are listed as advisory committee members of the NYLSF. Flyers showing the issues of concern to the League included the military's rules on sexuality and invasion of privacy; freedom to be nude; the rights of publishers, booksellers, and motion picture makers to create and distribute erotica; the defense of comedian Lenny Bruce; the Village Voice refusing to advertise a lesbian event; homosexual rights; legalizing prostitution; rights for prisoners; wife swapping and the swinging lifestyle; and a campaign to liberalize the policies of the Reference division of the NY Public Library. Also a flyer announcing Ralph Ginzburg speaking about his erotic magazine Eros, and newspaper clippings.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
William Goring was a radical anarchist and founding member of the Columbia University chapter of the New York City League for Sexual Freedom, also called the Sexual Freedom League, an organization founded in 1963 in New York City by Jefferson Poland and Leo Koch. The organization promoted sexual activity among its members and agitated for political reform, especially for the repeal of laws against abortion and censorship. It contributed to the sexual revolution of the 1960s, a cultural and political movement that challenged traditional codes of behavior related to sexuality and interpersonal relationships. Goring joined the mailing list for the radical feminist group called the October 17th Movement, named after the date that women from the New York City chapter of NOW decided to form it. Later known as The Feminists, the group sought to create a new kind of feminist movement, one with starkly different attitudes about sexuality and the sexual revolution than those of the League for Sexual Freedom. The Feminists highlighted the oppressive nature for women of both male sexuality and existing gender roles. Ti-Grace Atkinson was the group's central figure and informal leader until she left the group in 1971. Other prominent members included Anne Koedt, Sheila Michaels, Barbara Mehrhof, Pamela Kearon, and Sheila Cronan.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Files about the NYC League for Sexual Freedom, all from 1964, including a proposal for its structure dated 20 April 1964, and a pink mimeographed rough draft of this proposal with handwritten notes. Seven letters to and from Goring about the League, 1 from Jefferson Poland. Danny Sloan wrote to William Goring about Sloan's recent broadcast with Barry Gray on December 14th. On the letterhead, Allen Ginsberg and others are listed as advisory committee members of the NYLSF. Flyers showing the issues of concern to the League included the military's rules on sexuality and invasion of privacy; freedom to be nude; the rights of publishers, booksellers, and motion picture makers to create and distribute erotica; the defense of comedian Lenny Bruce; the Village Voice refusing to advertise a lesbian event; homosexual rights; legalizing prostitution; rights for prisoners; wife swapping and the swinging lifestyle; and a campaign to liberalize the policies of the Reference division of the NY Public Library. Also a flyer announcing Ralph Ginzburg speaking about his erotic magazine Eros, and newspaper clippings.
Typed statements of The Feminists, including their manifesto, organizational principles and structure, and essays written by the founders, Ti-Grace Atkinson, Barbara Mehrhof and Sheila Cronan, and other members, from circa 1968-1970.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Goring, William.; Atkinson, Ti-Grace.; Bruce, Lenny.; Cronan, Sheila.; Ginsberg, Allen.; Ginzburg, Ralph.; Mehrhof, Barbara.; Poland, Jefferson F.
Subjects:
Armed Forces -- Sexual conduct.; Censorship.; Feminism.; Gays.; Homosexuality.; Lesbian separatism; Lesbians.; Nudism.; Privacy.; Radical feminism.; Sexism.; Sexual freedom.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Related material in collection #7624, Barry Gray Show debate on homosexuality.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. New York City League for Sexual Freedom
  - 3 copies of a proposal for structure of NYC League for Sexual Freedom, 1964-04-20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pink mimeographed rough draft of proposal for the Structure of NYC League for Sexual Freedom, 1964-04-16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    With handwritten notes
  - Flyer stating "Prisoners Should Not Help Prisons Operate", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flyer stating "We Protest Raids on Films", 1964-03-21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In response to filmmaker Jonas Mekas being arrested for exhibiting "Flaming Creatures"
  - 4 copies of a flyer calling for "Sex Rights for Prisoners", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 4 copies of a flyer to "Library Patrons", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Campaign to liberalize the policies of the Reference division of the NY Public Library
  - Flyer presenting Albert Ellis speaking on wife swapping, LeMetro Coffe House, 1964-01-17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Ellis, Albert
  - 5 handwritten flyers with illustrations depicting women carrying protest signs, 1964-04-12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In response to the incarceration of prostitutes
  - 5 copies of a pink flyer, "wanting volunteers to go to Jail for the freedom of press", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flyer announcing the 5th meeting of NYC League for Sexual Freedom, 1964-04-25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Also states talk by Larry Cole
  - 3 copies of flyer "Join The N.Y.C. League for Sexual Freedom", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flyer for talk by Randolph Wicker, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Handwritten map on verso revealing other events at various locations
    Wicker, Randolph
  - Torn page stating proposed chapter of Sexual Freedom Forum, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Listing of members by name and address - Sexual Freedom Forum of Columbia University, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flyer announcing a meeting that will include discussion on a number of listed topics, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flyer, "...Let me take your kids to a dirty movie", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    With excerpts from Lenny Bruce's autobiography from Playboy and Paul Krassner's editorial from the Realist
  - 4 copies of a flyer asking their peers to "Join us in protesting against Operation Yorkville!", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Blank petition to the Honorable Robert F. Wagner, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Wagner, Robert F.
  - Flyer announcing Ralph Ginzburg speaking on the act of worship as a sexual rite, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Ginzburg, Ralph
  - 5 postcards with handwritten notes and three addresses of potential members, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 3 flyers in an envelope addressed to Bill Goring, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Army invades sexual privacy", "Talkout busted", "Four lesbians discuss their lives"
  - Flyer "March for Sex Rights For Prisoners" with small map of meeting location, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Very fragile: flyer titled "Attention: culture maker and cats paw, REWARD", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contains hand written notes along with an illustration of a bunny in pen; accompanied with envelope stamped "Pumpkin Papers", "Confidential"
  - Signed typed letter from Danny Sloan to Goring regarding broadcast with Barry Gray, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Sloan, Danny
  - Typed letter by Jefferson Poland regarding defending and expanding rights of nudists, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Poland, Jefferson
  - Signed typed letter from Miss Sharon K. Ellis, 1964-05-16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Ellis, Sharon K.
  - Signed typed letter from Goring in reply to Miss Ellis, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Goring's copy of a two-page, typed mimeograph letter regarding political issues to address, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Signed typed letter from John Slonski in Australia to Goring and John Konheim regarding "sex freedom" campaign, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Slonski, John
    Konheim, John
  - Signed typed letter from Judy Mathe of The Daily Collegian requesting information/problems with University administration, 1964-05-06 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Mathe, Judy
  - Issue #4 and #5 of GRP News sent to Goring from California chapter of GRP, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes xerox copy of Goring’s return letter
  - Newspaper clippings about NYLSF, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes 1 issue of the Columbia Spectator, vol. CIX - No. 1 New York
- Series II. The Feminists
  - History of the Feminists, 1970-01 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Organizational principles and structure, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Radical feminism, Undated; Atkinson, Ti-Grace (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vaginal orgasm as a mass hysterical survival response, Undated; Atkinson, Ti-Grace (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rules and responsibility in a leaderless revolutionary (feminist) group, 1969-09; Kearson, Pamela (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The rise of man: the origin of woman's oppression: one view, 1969-12; Mehrhof, Barbara; Cronan, Sheila (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The archetypal woman, Undated; Michaels, Sheila (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The story of the amazons, Undated; Diner, Helen (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Reprinted from Mothers and Amazons
  - The twig benders, Undated; Chase, Wilds (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notes from the lower classes, Undated; Schwartz, Rosalind (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notes from the lower classes II, Undated; Cleary, Josephine (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dangers in the pro-women line and consciousness-raising, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Man-hating, Undated; Kearon, Pamela (Box 1, Folder 3)